Okay בוקר
טוב *boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is קס"ט *Kof Samech Tes*, 169.
We pick up on the top of קס"ט *Kof Samech Tes* and
I guess
we'll just quickly read from the bottom of קס"ח עמוד ב' *Kof
Samech Ches Amud Beis* just to review what we did yesterday because
it's going to be the focus of the whole דף *daf* today
is the ברייתא *braita* at the bottom of this. So here's what
the ברייתא *braita* says: תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan* הרי שבא ואמר אבד
שטר shtar, חובי *Harei sheba ve'amar avad shtar chovi*. Somebody comes and
says that I lost
my the writ that I had that somebody owes me a thousand
dollars. אף על פי שאמרו עדים אנו חתמנו ונתנו בו *Af al
pi she'amru eidim anu chasamnu venasanu bo*, even if the witnesses testified
that yes, indeed, we were the witnesses on that שטר shtar, *shtar*
and we know that this person borrowed the money,
totally legit, such a שטר shtar? *shtar* actually exists, אין כותבין ein
kotvin. אותו שטר shtar *ein kosvin oso shtar*, you do not write
a replacement שטר shtar. *shtar*. Because even if he's telling the truth,
and first of all he might be lying, but even if he's
telling the truth,
he might find the שטר shtar *shtar* that he's missing
and then he'll have two שטרות shtaros *shtarot* that say that this
person owes him a thousand dollars, so whatever, he'll collect twice. So
you don't do that. במה דברים אמורים בשטרי הלואה *Bamei devarim amurim
b'shtarei halvaa*, if it's a loan document. אבל בשטרי מקח וממכר כותבין
חוץ מן אחריות achrayus שבו *Aval b'shtarei mekach u'mimkar kosvin chutz min
achrayus shebo*. So I have a document that says I bought from
Charlie his field and then I say I lost it. So what's
the concern? I mean, I do own the field,
so who could I be cheating? So basically, the only concern, first
thing is that you would have to write the
document from the original date. This is if the witnesses testify that
indeed this happened, we have concrete proof that this happened. Okay, because
if you write a document, let's say from today, then the point
would be I bought the שטר shtar *shtar*, sold it back to
Charlie, and now I'm bringing out the שטר shtar *shtar* with today's
date that says that I bought it back from him again, so
right, that is a possible abuse if you have it at a
different date. But if it has the original date, what's the concern?
So the only concern would be that every document of a sale
has in it explicitly or implicitly the fact that you can go
ahead and get reimbursed if the field gets taken away, if the
field gets seized because of payment of a loan. I bought this
field from Charlie, some creditors came, it took it from me, I'm
going to go get it back and get reimbursed from Charlie for
that field. Okay, so in that type of a case, if I
have two שטרות shtaros *shtarot* and for the same field and the
same date and they both have in it the אחריות achrayus *achrayus*,
the insurance, then what I will do is I will collect
from one of
Charlie's the people that bought Charlie's property from him because if I
can get reimbursed from Charlie, then I also have liens on the
property he sells other people. So in one case I'll produce one
שטר shtar, *shtar* to collect the field to say, look, this field
was taken from me, here's the שטר shtar, *shtar* that I owned
the field, I'm taking your stuff in reimbursement for that field, and
then I will forfeit that שטר shtar *shtar* and then I'll take
the other שטר shtar, *shtar* and collect somebody else's field as a
result, both people that Charlie sold his fields to. Okay, so that's
why you can rewrite it, but you can't have it have the
insurance in it, the אחריות achrayus. *achrayus*, because then nobody is at
risk, right? You understand?
Okay, here's this field.
Here's the
seller, I'll use some different colors. Okay, here am I, I'm the
buyer, and here's my שטר shtar *shtar*. Okay, now, if it's got
אחריות achrayus. *achrayus* in it,
okay, then that means and I bought this field, okay, then that
means that if the field gets taken from me to pay up
some debt, okay,
here's he owes him a thousand
dollars, okay, so he's gonna now seize the field, I'll do it
like this, he's gonna seize that field to take pay off his
debt. Okay, because of this אחריות achrayus. *achrayus*, I can go ahead
and get my money back from the seller. Now, if the seller
doesn't have any money, then I can also get my money back
from people that the seller has sold other fields to. Okay, because
once I bought this field at this date, that created liens on
his property, and if he sold this stuff afterwards, right, then I
have liens on that property for reimbursement if the field gets taken
from me. So lo and behold this field gets taken from me,
I go ahead and I get a piece of property back as
reimbursement and I forfeit the שטר shtar *shtar*. Okay, now, if we
go ahead and I lose the שטר shtar? *shtar* and you write
me another one with אחריות achrayus *achrayus*, and either I'm lying or
I find the original one, then what I can do is I
can go ahead and say look, the field is no longer mine,
you can see because this guy over here is now in possession
of the field, so it's no longer mine so it was taken
from me in payment of debt. Okay, and therefore, I'm entitled to
go ahead and get reimbursed from the seller, but the seller doesn't
have it, so I'm gonna get reimbursed with my liens from you.
So I say this to this guy and give him this שטר,
shtar then I say the second thing to the second guy and
with that שטר, shtar, and I collect twice. So, in order to
prevent that, if I say that I've lost my שטר, shtar, we'll
write another one with me, but it won't have the אחריות achrayus
in it. And because it doesn't have the אחריות achrayus. in it,
if I go to this other guy, what am I going to
do with this other שטר? shtar This שטר shtar, says that I
bought this field a year ago. Okay, big deal, it's now been
seized or whatever. So, and now I can't use it to get
reimbursed because it doesn't have the right of reimbursement. So, that's why
you're allowed to go ahead and write that second שטר.
shtar The second שטר shtar?
serves
just because I claimed that this is lost. So, what the שטר
shtar, serves is that I prove that I own the field. It's
not going to protect me. I'm not going to be able to
reinstitute my אחריות.
achrayus, Just that you own it helps you if
someone's exactly, but you know what, that's why I'm, supposedly my own
fault I lost my document. Okay. אבל שטר מכר שמכרו כותבין חוץ
מן אחריות שבו. aval shtar mecher shemachru kotvin chutz min achrayus shebo.
ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף שטר מכר שמכרו אין כותבין. ve-rabban
shimon ben gamliel omer af shtar mecher shemachru ein kotvin. No,
you can't even write a replacement even without אחריות. achrayus, Why? אין
כותבין. וכן היה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, ve-chein haya rabban shimon
ben gamliel omer, הנותן מתנה לחבירו והחזיר לו את השטר חזרה מתנתו.
ha-noten matana l'chaveiro ve-hechezir lo es ha-shtar chazra matanaso.
Thank you. אבל חכמים אומרים מתנתו קיימת. aval chachamim omrim matanaso kayames.
Why? Because רבן שמעון בן גמליאל rabban shimon ben gamliel said that
if you, if basically if I were to give this שטר shtar.
back to the seller, my original שטר, shtar it would actually reverse
the sale. Okay. So, he says that that sort of works, we'll
see where in the גמרא, gemara, but the same way basically you
can sell land with a שטר, shtar, so by giving back the
original שטר shtar, to the seller, it symbolically is a reversal of
the sale, it gives him the land back. So, if that's true,
he says, if you say you don't have the שטר, shtar we're
not going to believe you because maybe the reason you don't have
the שטר shtar. is you gave it back to the seller. And
now you're going to write another שטר shtar and then you're going
to claim that you never gave it back to the seller. Okay.
So, now of course the question is how you're going to explain
the fact though that the seller has the original שטר? shtar Okay.
So, תוספות tosafos has a great answer. He says, look, the הלכה
halacha is you can write a שטר shtar for the seller without
the buyer there. So, the seller instead could go ahead and have
gone to one סופר sofer and says, write me a שטר, shtar
I'm planning on selling the field, and then he goes to another
סופר sofer and says, write me a שטר, shtar, I'm planning on
selling the field. Okay. And he gives the שטר shtar. to this
guy. If this guy were ever to lose, תוספות tosafos is very
bothered with this because this is like just ripe for abuse. But
if this guy were ever to lose his שטר, shtar according to
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, rabban shimon ben gamliel, the seller could just
produce the other שטר shtar he had from the other סופר sofer
and say, ah, you know why he doesn't have his שטר? shtar,
He gave me back the שטר, shtar he gave me back the
field. So, that's a real problem. Okay. But anyway, what you don't,
you've got to hold onto your שטר. shtar Okay. But that's why
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל rabban shimon ben gamliel says that because if
you give back the שטר shtar. he can claim it's his, we're
not going to write you a replacement שטר, shtar because then what
you're going to say
is this, I never gave him back the שטר, shtar I always
owned it and the fact that he has it is just because
he had a copy written for himself. All right. So, therefore, basically
what it means is that so according to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
rabban shimon ben gamliel, he's only believed if he's holding onto the
original שטר shtar. to say it's his if the guy doesn't have
himself a שטר. shtar, All right. So, anyway, he says, you can't
write this guy a backup שטר shtar because then he will, it's
possible that the reason he doesn't have the original שטר shtar, was
he gave it back to the seller, now owned by the seller,
and writing him another שטר shtar, will allow him to claim that
it's his. Okay, that's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל rabban shimon ben
gamliel says. But the חכמים chachamim say giving back the שטר shtar
to the seller does not make the seller own it and therefore
even if the seller's holding onto a שטר, shtar we wouldn't assume
his ownership over it. So, therefore, you are entitled to get a
שטר. shtar. It doesn't matter what happened to your original one, you're
entitled to get a replacement שטר shtar as long as it doesn't
have אחריות. achrayos. Okay. So, the אחריות achrayus, puts at risk these
guys. So, if you say you lost it, we cannot go ahead
and write another one with אחריות achrayus, because maybe you didn't or
maybe you'll find it. But the question is, we are prepared to
write it to protect yourself. That's what the חכמים chachamim say. So
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל rabban shimon ben gamliel says not because he's
concerned about the case that the reason you don't have it is
you gave it back to the owner and that reversed the sale.
Okay. So now the גמרא gemara says like this. אמר
מר. amar mar. Now we're going to unpack this.
חוץ מאחריות שבו. chutz mei-achrayus shebo. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the
reason? אמר רב ספרא לפי שאין כותבין שני שטרות על שדה אחת
amar rav safra lefi she-ein kotvin shnei shtaros al sadei achas because
you don't write two שטרות for the same field, both with אחריות.
achrayus, דלמא אזיל בעל חוב וטרף ליה להאי. dilma azil ba'al chov
ve-taraf lei l'hai. See, now I already, I already drew it out
for you. lest בעל חוב ba'al chov וקם ve-kam and seized the
field.
ואזיל האי ומפיק חד וטרף ללקוחות ve-azil hai u-mafik chad ve-taraf l'lakochos
and this guy will come and he will, I will use this
שטר shtar to get from this guy who bought. from the seller
I have liens on it. ואמר ליה לבעל חוב, v'amar lei l'ba'al
chov, now I'll say to the בעל חוב, ba'al chov, now שוף
לי דאיקום בה. shof li d'eikum bah. Now I'll say to the
בעל חוב, ba'al chov, I'll say to this guy, you know what,
wait, wait, hold on, I gotta make sure I got this right,
this בעל
חוב.
ba'al chov.
Right, I will say to him, listen, listen, because here's the thing.
In order for me to get from these guys, I have to
come with a claim that I have to say the field was
taken from me, right? So the problem is I've got to get
this guy to be in on my scheme, because if I go
to you and I say the field was taken from me, you'll
say, well how do I know the field was taken from you?
Then well go ahead and look, ask the creditor.
He's got his שטר, shtar he'll show you that he has a
right to seize the field from בית דין. Beis Din.
So the creditor comes and
shows that, you know, he had from בית דין Beis Din a
right to seize this field in payment of the debt that this
guy owed him. Okay, so you see he's took my field and
I have this שטר shtar, with אחריות, achrayus so now I'm going
to take this. So you need the creditor to, you know, show
that genuinely this field was taken from me in payment of a
debt and I'm entitled to reimbursement. So now what I've got to
do is, I want to go back, what? This is the... No,
he's the creditor. He is the guy
that this person,
ראובן, Reuven, was the original owner here. He owes שמעון Shimon this
money. Okay, שמעון Shimon came and said where's my thousand dollars? I
don't have it, fine, I'm taking away the field that you sold
to Doe. Okay, I go to them and I say I'm entitled
to get reimbursed because ראובן Reuven insured that field and from me,
and the field was taken from me and I'm entitled to get
reimbursed. So they say how do I know it was taken from
you? So I mean, I'm not...
I see somebody on your field, maybe you hired him. How do
I know it was seized from you that I should reimburse you
for it? So then I get שמעון Shimon to come and show
that he's got a writ from בית דין Beis Din that ראובן
Reuven did not pay his debt and that he's entitled to seize
any of ראובן's Reuven fields that he has a lien on in
payment of ראובן's Reuven debts. And he shows that to the guy
and he shows that he seized this property. And I therefore I
prove to him that this property was seized from me in payment
of ראובן's Reuven debt and therefore I'm coming to you to for
reimbursement. Okay, so I've got to get, so שמעון's Shimon got to
be, like, might be called to bring evidence, you know, or to
back up my story that this field was seized by him in
payment of ראובן's Reuven debt and I'm entitled for reimbursement. So now,
I use that with guy number one. With guy number one, it
was true. Now I go with my שטר shtar number two to
guy number two. It's not true with guy number two. Guy number
two's going to say how do I know that field was seized
from you in payment of debt? So I'm going to have to
get שמעון Shimon to play along with me, right? You got this?
In order for me to now be able to also collect from
guy number two. All right, so that's the basic point.
What happens when this fellow in an honest way seizes the field
of one of those people on the left, right? Yeah. And then
somebody comes and says this field is mine, you know, I have
rights to it because this person, you know, didn't pay up his
debt and they take the field from him.
So one more time, what happens on what?
When this fellow, right, he goes up, he goes to take one
of those fields and he receives it. Right. And then what happens
if somebody comes, a creditor of that person, and says this field,
I'm taking your field because...
Yeah, I mean whatever, it could all go in a big circle.
I mean, you have to determine who has the earlier lien. I
mean, the funny thing is that after if they've also bought this
from ראובן Reuven with אחריות, achrayus, then they're going to go back
to ראובן, Reuven, if he doesn't have a field they're going to
go to the next person ראובן Reuven sold to. So it's sort
of like everybody's passing the buck to the next person. Okay now,
now what I just described was what the גמרא's Gemara going to
discuss in a minute, which is I try to do the two
of them on the same day and to get שמעון Shimon to
play along with me, you know, first go to this guy, which
is true, and then to this guy, which isn't. But the גמרא
Gemara is actually first saying, you know, that's what the גמרא's Gemara
going to say is that's going to raise suspicions, going to two
people like roughly at the same time for the same claim. Okay,
so what I actually say to שמעון Shimon to play along is
not just back up my story, but I actually tell him, look,
I know it's your field, let me stand the field for another
year or two or three or whatever it is, okay, and then
come back and take the field again and we'll go through the
whole like little process again. Okay, and then I'll get it from
this guy. At that stage people will have forgotten, you know, hopefully
what happened before, so people, you know, they won't realize that you'd
already seized it a few years ago and I got paid from
the other guy. All right, so rather than just say come and
claim whatever, it doesn't happen at all, like let me hold on
to it for a few years and we'll go through the whole
thing again and we'll split the difference. Okay, so ואמר ליה לבעל
חוב v'amar lei l'ba'al chov שוף לי, shof li, like you know,
like, like, like, what's a good translation of that? Like you know
what, yeah, it says like שוף לי. shof li. שופ shof is
like good, like it says, you know, like go easy on me
essentially, or like leave me undisturbed.
Leave me undisturbed, right.
Okay, like leave it alone. ואקום בה, ve'akum bah, let me stay
in the field for a little
while, והדר תירפא, ve'hadar tirfa, and then I will then then come
and take it from me again, technically you've already taken from me
and I've collected from this guy, but let's keep that on the
quiet. Then a little while later take it from me
again, okay, ואעלמתא, ve'aalmata, and I'll go ahead and collect from the
second guy with my second שטר. shtar ומפיק אחרינא והדר וטרף ללקוחות
אחריני u'mapik achrina ve'hadar u'tarof le'lekuchos achrini and I'll take out the
other
שטר shtar and I'll go collect from the
other לקוחות, lekuchos, okay? דכיון דקרעינא לשטרא דמלוה, dekivan dekar'ina leshtara demalve,
so now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. The גמרא Gemara says
how's that going to work? Because what's going to happen? As soon
as שמעון Shimon goes to collect this field, he's collecting it because
ראובן Reuven owes him some money, right? So what's ראובן Reuven going
to demand? ראובן's Reuven going to demand that שטר shtar, that I
owe you the money. Now that you've collected this field, you have
to tear up that שטר. shtar Okay?
So once you've torn up the שטר, shtar how are you going
to go through the process again? Okay?
דמאי הדר טרף ליה? demai hadar taraf leh?
So how are you going to go ahead and collect it
again,
okay? Yeah, but now you're going to have to get ראובן Reuven
in on the scheme as well.
ראובן Reuven is the one perpetrating the scheme.
No, ראובן Reuven isn't perpetrating the scheme. ראובן Reuven just gave me
another שטר shtar, because I said I lost mine. ראובן Reuven doesn't
want to be part... if ראובן Reuven wants to be part of
this, ראובן Reuven can do, you know, if everybody's part of it,
you can get away with whatever you want.
ראובן Reuven just wrote me a שטר, shtar he doesn't want all
these people that he sold to have their field taken. It's me
and שמעון Shimon that are part of the scheme. Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says והא קרעינא, veha kar'ina, so דכי תימא דלא קרעינא,
dechiteima delo kar'ina, maybe, you know, you won't tear up the
שטר, shtar ואמר רב נחמן כל טירפא דלא כתיב ביה קרעינא לשטרא
דמלוה לאו טירפא הוא. ve'amar Rav Nachman kol tirfa delo kasiv beh
kar'ina leshtara demilve lav tirfa hu.
No,
we won't allow שמעון Shimon to seize the field unless we actually
tear up the original IOU. That's being protecting ראובן. Reuven. Okay? So
any, so basically what would happen is ראובן Reuven would come and
say, שמעון Shimon would come and say here's the thousand dollars ראובן
Reuven owes me, I want to seize property. So בית דין Beis
Din will substitute that שטר shtar that says ראובן Reuven owes him
a thousand dollars and give him what's called a טירפא. tirfa. טירפא
tirfa basically is like, you know, it's like a writ that allows
him to seize this property, and they'll say fine, we're going to
give you a writ that allows you to seize this property but
we're going to have to, before we give you that writ, tear
up the things that says that ראובן Reuven owes you a thousand
dollars. Okay, so the writ says we hereby authorize שמעון Shimon to
seize this piece of property in payment of the debt and we
tore up the original שטר shtar document. Okay, that's what it would
have to say. כל טירפא, kol tirfa, any seizing document דלא כתיב
ביה delo kasiv beh that's not written inside of it, קרעינא לשטרא
דמלוה, kar'ina leshtara demilve, we've torn up the original debt
note לאו טירפא הוא, lav tirfa hu,
is not a legitimate document to seize property. דכל אדרכתא דלא כתיב
ביה קרעינא לטירפא לאו אדרכתא היא. dechol adrachta delo kasiv beh kar'ina
letirfa lav adrachta hi.
And any אדרכתא, adrachta, the אדרכתא adrachta is what's the אדרכתא adrachta
after the טירפא? tirfa? Hold on. One minute.
Oh, I'm sorry, so it's three stages. First the טירפא tirfa says
that,
the טירפא tirfa first says that we're giving שמעון Shimon the right
to find property and identify property under that ראובן Reuven had or
that he has liens on. Okay? And then we tear up the
שטר. shtar, Then שמעון Shimon comes and he says I identified this
particular piece of property. This is the one that I have liens
on, that can pay up my debt, etc. Then we replace the
טירפא tirfa with an אדרכתא. adrachta. The אדרכתא adrachta is the more
specific document that specifically identifies this particular field itself. Okay? That's
the אדרכתא. adrachta. Okay,
and each שטר shtar has to explicitly replace the previous one because
obviously you don't want to allow the guy to reuse the document
for more than one field. Okay? So כל טירפא דלא כתיב ביה
קרעינא לשטרא דמלוה לאו טירפא הוא. kol tirfa delo kasiv beh kar'ina
leshtara demilve lav tirfa hu. So the טירפא tirfa allows him to
go ahead and to identify property. And then כל אדרכתא, kol adrachta,
the אדרכתא adrachta which basically gives him rights to a particular piece
of property דלא כתיב ביה delo kasiv beh that's not written in
it קרעינא לטירפא, kar'ina letirfa, we tore up the טירפא tirfa לאו
אדרכתא היא, lav adrachta hi, that's not a legitimate document of seizing.
דכל שומא דלא כתיב ביה קרעינא לאדרכתא לאו שומא היא. dechol shuma
delo kasiv beh kar'ina leadrachta lav shuma hi. And then the שומא
shuma finally assesses the exact value because let's say for example that
this field is worth I don't know nine hundred dollars and not
a thousand dollars. So the אדרכתא adrachta gives him rights to the
field and the שומא shuma basically says, you know something like this
field was taken in payment of the debt. of nine hundred dollars
of the debt. Like apparently it's a different stage, I don't know
why, like I don't know why you wouldn't sort of roll it
all into one, but it's a different stage than the right to
seize the property is the assessment of how much the property exactly
was worth and therefore how much of the debt that it paid
off. Okay. So those are the different types of documents. Each one
replaces the other but basically the documents that give him right to
take this would mean that he would not have the original שטר
shtar? anymore. So how are you going to go through the process
again? Okay. I don't exactly get the question because as long as
he still has the process to seize the property why do you
need the שטר חוב shtar chov again? But let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay. לא צריכה דקאתי
מכח דאבהתיה.
lo tzricha
d'ka'asi mi'koach d'avasai. So no, the case is not a case where
it was a case of a sale but a case of a
claim of original ownership of the fathers. Let me just double check
the רש"י Rashi here again. Keep on getting confused with this, hold
on. Oh,
well first of all, I think the point was, I think the
point was was that once he finally takes the field, before we
get onto the answer, since every שטר shtar excuse me
gets torn up to replace the next one when you get to
the next stage, so when he finally seizes the field you know
the שטר, shtar, all the שטרות he had that gave him the
right to seize the field are now like torn up, right? So
everything is torn up so you don't use it twice is the
basic point. Okay. So I'm not exactly sure, I think the שומא
shuma might just say how much of the debt has like now
been paid off but but the point but the point is that
if I come back again, if we wait and I come to
try to seize it again, what do what does שמעון Shimon have
left to seize the field? He doesn't have the original
שטר חוב, shtar chov, he doesn't have the בית דין Beis Din
gave him to seize the field. Once he actually takes possession, the
documents that gave him that right are torn up so he doesn't
apparently reuse it I think seems to be the point. So therefore
if that's true how can he go ahead and later claim that
he's reseizing the field? Okay. And how come we go through the
whole rigmarole again if he has no documentation that would give him
right to do that? Is that pretty much clear to people, yes?
All right. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is דאבהתיה d'avasai which means
what?
Right. Yeah,
it's because what we're afraid of is that not that שמעון Shimon
is going to say he's owed the money from ראובן, Reuven, he's
going to prove that this was always his field, okay. He's going
to say that ראובן Reuven stole it. ראובן Reuven stole it,
it belonged to my
fathers to my fathers and let's say that's true, okay, sometimes you
know I mean a lot of things with title searches or whatever
with land there's a lot of land that's like you know held
up for many many years because there's a question of exactly proving
who owns it. Okay. So he genuinely proves that and he takes
it. Okay. So now I'm entitled to get reimbursed. It doesn't matter
if it was taken from me because of a debt or taken
from me because of whatever. So I'm entitled to get reimbursed. I
go to him and I get reimbursed. Okay. Then I go back
to שמעון Shimon and I say שמעון, Shimon, you know what? Let
me stay on the field for a while and you'll people will
sort of forget about it or whatever, I'll hold on to it
and then you'll come back again and you'll make the claim that
it belonged to your father. So that's not like a חוב. chov.
That's not like something that you have a right to seize property
and then you have to tear it up. That's really proving it
was originally yours and it was stolen from you. So we can
do that a second time maybe in a second בית דין, Beis
Din, they won't know about this previous thing and that'll entitle me
to go ahead and get reimbursed and I'll go ahead and use
my other שטר shtar, here to get reimbursed. Okay. So that's the
concern. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא ולמה ליה למימר ליה לבעל חוב
שופלי ובהאי ארעא ואיקום בה.
amar lei Rav Acha Midifti l'Ravina v'lama lei l'meimar lei l'ba'al chov
shofli v'behai ara v'eikum bah. Why does he have to say you
know leave it by me for a while?
Why can't we just do them both on the same day you
know one right after the other?
Excuse me. תיפוק ליה דכיון דנקיט תרי שטרי טרף והדר טרף.
tipok lei d'keivan d'nakit teri
shtarei taraf v'hadar taraf. Right. Why do I have to say I'll
stay on the field for a while and then you'll come back
again and you'll say oh it was stolen from me yadda yadda
yadda, right? Why don't we just go back the next day and
I'll do it again? So the גמרא Gemara says no. אם כן
נפישי ליה בעלי דינין. im hachi nefishi lei ba'alei dinin. Then I'm
going to get involved in a lot of court cases all at
once and and word's going to get out you know the word'll
travel and people will find out that I'm trying to collect twice.
So therefore what I'll do is
collect once, lay low,
שמעון Shimon will let me hold on to the field for a
while, people will forget, we'll go to a different בית דין Beis
Din a few years from now we'll go through the whole thing
again.
Anyway that's why you don't write a second שטר shtar. if they
both have אחריות. achrayus
So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. וליכתוב להאי שטר מעליא וליכתוב תובנא למוכר. v'lichtov l'hai shtar ma'alya
v'lichtov tavna l'mocher. So I don't get it since גמרא. Gemara. Why
not? Because still, okay, we get why we're trying to protect these
לקוחות lakuchos from some scheme I might have or from the fact
even if I'm telling the truth, I might wind up that I
sign the שטר shtar, and then you know I can't resist the
temptation. But it's a little נעבעך nebech for me if I really
do lose my שטר, shtar, now I'm gonna lose out my אחריות,
achrayus, okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says wait, I've got a way that we
can give me another שטר shtar with אחריות, achrayus help me protect
my investment. And how are we going to protect everybody else here?
Because what we're going to do is I am going in the
second שטר Shtar, we're going to explicitly say or we're going to
give forget that second שטר, Shtar, we're going to give ראובן Reuven
a document that is going to be very explicit about what we
did. And here's the document that we're going to give ראובן. Reuven.
גמרא Gemara says like this: ולכתוב להאי שטר מעליא ולכתוב תברא למוכר.
V'lichtov l'hai shtar ma'alya v'lichtov tavra l'mocher.
Go give ראובן Reuven a receipt and here's what the receipt will
say: כל שטרי דיפקו על ארעא דא
פסולין,
Kol shtarei d'yaifku al ar'ah
da psulin, any documents that דוב Dov might bring, you know, that
shows that he owns this land or he bought this land are
invalid, לבר מן דיפוק בזמנא דא, l'var min d'yaifuk b'zimna da, except
the one that came like at this time, meaning like in this
שטר Shtar. we'll basically say something like, this שטר shtar was written
as a replacement of the original one blah blah blah. So we'll
date this שטר shtar you know something like I don't know, July
1st, and this replaces the שטר shtar, that was written on you
know whatever, December 10th, okay? And then here we're going to write
you a document that's going to say, you know, any bill of
sale, any bill of sale
you know that דוב Dov has, you know is invalid except for
the one that says that it was done on July 1 to
replace the one from December 10th. Okay. So, well, I guess that's
true. Any bill of sale that I have about December 10th is
invalid except for the one that says you know the replacement one,
okay? So that means that if I ever try to produce this,
it's invalid. If I try to produce this, it also has the
December 10th date. Right, I mean I could have another one, but
any field that I said I bought it on December 10th, the
only valid one is the replacement
one. If he ever tries to produce an original, it's invalid. Okay,
so why don't we just do that and then everybody will be
protected? Now that means that anytime I'm going to go ahead and
try to seize property, the seller is going to get pulled into
the case. Quick case, and you'll be able to produce you know
the receipt. But in the previous scenario I was waiting for somebody
to ask me this, in the previous scenario we spoke about me
going straight to these people and you know I had a whole
deal going on with שמעון. Shimon. The question I'm always asking myself
is, I'll have to go straight to these people without involving ראובן
Reuven in the discussion? I mean is ראובן Reuven part of the
scheme? He's not part of the scheme. But the question is why
was I able to leapfrog him? He's not part of the scheme.
But somehow originally the גמרא Gemara assumed that like I don't know,
somehow I was able to just directly go to them. But if
I involved ראובן Reuven in the discussion, you know ראובן Reuven would
have said, "What are you doing? He's a cheat! He's got two
separate documents etc." So the
earlier scenario somehow imagined that once he's deceased and I've got the
אחריות, achrayus. I can somehow not involve ראובן. Reuven. This scenario imagines
that ראובן Reuven will be involved. And rather than to make it
better, not just that ראובן Reuven will call me out on it,
because he'll call me a liar, I'll call him a liar, so
that you know maybe we ignored that before, but here it says
rather than just calling me out on it, let's give him documentation.
And therefore if ראובן Reuven is always going to be involved, he'll
produce
the documentation that will make it that I can't use the other
שטר, shtar, okay?
So that's a good question. So the גמרא Gemara says: כל שטרי
דיפקו על ארעא דא פסולין לבר מן דיפוק בזמנא דא. Kol shtarei
d'yaifku al ar'ah da psulin l'var min d'yaifuk b'zimna da. So why
don't we do
that? So אמרו רבנן קמי דרב פפא, Amru rabanan kmei d'Rav Pappa,
so they said this to
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, why don't we write this שטר shtar with
אחריות Achrayut, and give the seller a documentation that'll invalidate the original
שטר? shtar ואמרוה קמי דרב אשי, V'amruha kmei d'Rav Ashi, and some
said to רב אשי: Rav Ashi: זאת אומרת, Zos omeres, so the
rabbis who said this said should we infer from the fact that
this isn't a solution, should we infer from this אין כותבין שובר,
Ein kosvin shovar, that the general rule is we do not write
receipts, right? Because there's a general question by writing who becomes the
person responsible, right? If we give the receipt to ראובן, Reuven, then
ראובן Reuven has to hold on to a document because I was
negligent and
sloppy. Right? So writing receipt,
if I lent אלי Eli money and then he pays up and
I want to get you know, excuse me, and אלי Eli pays
up and he wants to get the
שטר shtar, back, okay? So if I say I don't have the
שטר, shtar you know, but I'll write you a receipt, that's not
fair to him. Why should he have to hold on to that
receipt? Right, then if he loses the receipt, I'm going to just
secretly holding on to my שטר, shtar I'm going to collect from
him. So the same point is here. This isn't a solution. It
means because if to say we would write a receipt puts the
reseller now responsible for holding on to that. Rather, I should go
now, I was sloppy with my
שטר. shtar He shouldn't be the one that's responsible. If I was
sloppy with my שטר, shtar, just don't give me a replacement with
אחריות, achrayus, right? That I think that makes sense. Why give me
a replacement with אחריות achrayus and make him responsible for holding on
to the receipt? So that's what they're saying. Should we therefore infer
from this that since that isn't a solution, as a general rule
we don't write receipts? So אמר להו, Amar Lehu, so he said
back to them, no.
דעלמא כתבי שוברא. D'alma katvei shovra. Normally we would write receipts. והכא
היינו טעמא, V'hacha hainu ta'ama, here's why we don't. It's not, you
know, normally we might could make that the seller's responsible.
But there's going to be a way where the receipt won't cover
our bases. דדילמא אזיל בעל חוב וטרף מיניה דלוקח D'dilma azil ba'al
chov v'taref minei d'lokeach because what's going to happen is
that sometimes I, I'm not really a בעל חוב ba'al chov here,
but the תוספות Tosfos uses a בעל חוב ba'al chov because the
normal language of receipts are the לוה loveh and the בעל חוב.
ba'al chov. Okay, but what it means is I'm the one that's
owed money for being reimbursed for the field that was taken from
me. So what am I going to do? I'm going to go
וטרף מיניה דלוקח. v'taref minei d'lokeach. I'm going to go ahead and
get from the guy number one. וטרף מיניה דלוקח דאזיל איהו וטרף
לקוחות V'taref minei d'lokeach d'azil ihu v'taref l'kuchos and I'm going to
go and take from לקוחות. l'kuchos. ושובר גבי לקוחות ליכא. V'shover gabi
l'kuchos leika. So they basically say what we said before, which is
I'm going to leapfrog the seller. The seller holding the receipt is
all very nice, but let's say the seller's off in China. Okay,
and I can prove to a בית דין Beis Din that this
field was taken, that I have אחריות, Achrayus I'll be able to
collect from them. They don't have the receipt. The seller has the
receipt. So the receipt with the seller does no good unless he's
around and getting involved in the proceedings. But as we assumed before,
there are cases where he could somehow be leapfrogged and him holding
the receipt won't do us any good. Okay. ושובר גבי לקוחות ליכא.
V'shover gabi l'kuchos leika. סוף סוף, Sof sof, the גמרא Gemara says,
and so what, at the end of the day לקוחות לאו עמי
דארעא הדרי, L'kuchos lav amei d'ara hadri, so but at the end
of the day the
לקוחות, l'kuchos, the גמרא Gemara
is saying the seller is going to have to get involved. Why
is the seller going to have to get involved? Because I seized
the property from these guys. What are they going to now want
to do? What's their recourse? They want to go back to the
seller and get reimbursed. So even if he's off in China and
I was able to get from them without him being involved, they're
eventually going to pull him in, want to get reimbursed and he's
going to say what? You gave it to him twice? Wait, I
got this other thing, one of them wasn't valid and then that'll
get that whole thing reversed and I'll have to give it back.
Eventually he's going to get involved and eventually he'll be able to
prevent me from double usage. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אדהכי
והכי שמיט ואכיל פירי. Ad'hachi v'hachi shamit v'achil peiri. No, it's true
they will get him involved, they'll come back and try to get
that land that I took inappropriately, but in the interim I've been
living on that land for the last 10 years or eating the
פירות peiros for the last 10 years and you know now go
ahead and try to get that money back. I don't have it
on me. You know? So it's going to obviously make things very
difficult once the benefit that I received from it is no longer
around and I won't necessarily have assets to seize. Bottom line is
is that if I lost the שטר, shtar I cannot get אחריות
achrayus, and make this burden on everybody else and risk everybody else's
well-being and try to protect it with this receipt. No, I'm going
to have to get another שטר shtar. without אחריות. achrayus Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי Ei hachi says
אי נמי ei nami לוקח שלא באחריות lokeach shelo b'achrayus or the
גמרא Gemara says I'll give you a better example. Better example is
let's say they
don't have insurance, so then they'll never go back to him because
they were stupid enough to buy without insurance. So there's a way
that I can leapfrog the seller, take it from them and the
seller will never get involved. So having the seller have a receipt
doesn't do anything. Okay? Got that? All right. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אי הכי, Ei hachi,
if that's true that that's why we don't write a receipt here
because we're afraid that I will leapfrog the the the seller, but
normally we would write a receipt, the גמרא Gemara says wait, maybe
normally if I write a receipt I can also leapfrog the
seller. Okay. I lent Eli money. Eli pays me up, I give
him a receipt, okay? And then what I do is I still
have the שטר, shtar and I'm going to ignore Eli and I'm
going to go to people that bought the field off of Eli
and I'm going to go ahead and say Eli didn't pay me
up, here's my שטר, shtar, and I'm going to seize it. So
why can't- why aren't I afraid there that even though he has
a receipt, I'll just go straight to the people who bought the
fields from him that I have liens on and leapfrog over Eli
himself? So there's- okay. So let's see what the answer is. אי
הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, שטר חוב נמי Shtar chov
nami but don't act as well.
What good does it do to give the לוה Loveh the receipt
if the מלווה Malveh could basically just ignore the לוה? Loveh? So
the גמרא Gemara says no. התם זוזי
מסיק אמר פייסיה במלוה דזוזי.
Hatam zuzi
massik amar paisaie b'macho de-zuzi. הכא דארעא מסיק מי ידעי דמאן דמסיק
ארעא בזוזי לא מפייס. Hacha de-ara massik mi yad'ei de-man de-massik ara
be-zuzi lo m'fayis. So there, since basically I lent Eli money, hold
on, let me just check the רשב"ם Rashbam again to make sure
I'm getting this right.
Right. So therefore, because if I lent- if- if- if it were
a case here, but not the case of land, if it were
a case of just simple- okay.
Right.
Here's the מלווה, Malveh, here's the לוה. Loveh. I lent him
a
hundred- a thousand dollars, okay. Here the לקוחות, Lekuchot, okay. So it's
basically now he paid me back and I gave him a receipt.
Okay, here's the שובר. Shovar. All right. But now the question is
I still have the
שטר. shtar So I'm going to ignore him, go to the לקוחות,
Lekuchot, say look, he still owes me the money, I'm taking the
land. Okay. So the point is the לקוחות Lekuchot won't let me
do that. The לקוחות Lekuchot will say he owes you money. Okay,
we're not going to give you land- out of our land, unless
you can prove to us that he actually has not, you know,
you went to him first and he hasn't actually paid you cash.
First of all, your first- the first idea to get reimbursed was
with the cash. Land is like a backup. Okay. So they're going
to say I'm not giving you this קרקע Karka until we go
to the actual borrower, and they look, they would say it anyway,
right? I mean, that- you'd have to- then they- forgetting the idea
of money versus land, like why would I give you this thing
unless you can prove to me that the actual borrower doesn't have
any funds? Okay, so they're going to obviously involve the- the לוה
Loveh here, and therefore the לוה Loveh will have the שובר. Shovar.
Okay? Whereas the claim is, and this I don't exactly get, okay?
Again, this gets to our question of how do we leapfrog him.
Because the claim is they'll understand, look, you had a piece of
קרקע Karka taken from you, I get it. Your basic- and you're
basically what you're entitled to is not a reimbursement in cash, what
you're basically entitled to is a reimbursement in קרקע. Karka. So therefore
I get why you're coming straight to me. Okay. But what I
still don't understand is that even if I get that you want
קרקע Karka first, okay, like, we're only the backup. The primary person
responsible to you is the seller. So I still really do not
understand why it's ever possible to leapfrog and why if you're coming
to me, I can't insist that we first bring in the seller
and see if he has assets to pay you. And once we're
bringing in the seller, we'll see that he has a receipt. Okay,
so I really don't get- get that. Right. Either party is not
going to want to pay up. They're going to want to ensure
that you didn't first try to collect from- from the actual person
who directly owed you the money. But that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's claim.
The גמרא'ס Gemara's claim is here, I'm not- I'm going to refuse
to pay unless we involve the borrower, and here, since you got
land taken and you're entitled to land back, I might give you
my land without getting the bor- without getting the seller involved. Although
I really can't understand why that's true. Let's read it. Okay. גמרא
Gemara says like this. התם Hatam there, let's read that again. זוזי
מסיק Zuzi massik that money was borrowed, אמר פייסיה במלוה דזוזי. Amar
paisaie b'macho de-zuzi. So no, the- so- so I'll say that the-
the creditor was already paid up with money. And go prove to
me that the borrower didn't have money to pay you out because
you wanted cash. הכא דארעא מסיק Hacha de-ara massik here land's owed,
מי ידעי דמאן דמסיק ארעא בזוזי לא מפייס. Mi yad'ei de-man de-massik
ara be-zuzi lo m'fayis. They know that somebody who's owed land with
money will not be satisfied. But I still, but again, even if-
first of all it's interesting, that means that when you buy a
field with אחריות, achrayus if I let's say go to a seller,
and let's say he has cash on hand, is he allowed to
tell me- am I allowed to say, you know, am I allowed
to say I don't want your cash, I'd rather go to your
לקוחות Lekuchot because I'd rather get land than cash? Like our normal
assumption always is the לקוחות Lekuchot is only after the person who
directly owes the money has no way of paying. You would think
that whether he has cash or land or anything he has, that
if he can pay it up. you're not entitled to go to
the לקוחות. lakochos. Okay, that's number one. Number two is that even
if it's true, I would want his לקוחות lakochos to say, prove
to me that the seller doesn't have any land left. Like let's
go to the seller and get him involved. So I really don't
understand why here it's still possible to leapfrog, but that is somehow
the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. And תוספות Tosafos sort of asks that question. Look
at תוספות. Tosafos. דמסיק אריא בזוזי לא מסיק. Demasik arya bezuzi lo
masik. תימא, Teima, he says, ותימא לרי. Veteima LeRi. אם יכול המוכר
לסלקו בזוזי למה יניחו קרקעם, Im yachol hamocher lesalko bezuzi lama yanichu
karkam, right, if the seller has money, why will they allow their
fields to be taken? אפילו הכי יודעים שלא פרע לו השטר דהיינו
שיכולין לומר שינתן לו קרקע ומזיק אין לו יחזיר עליהם. Afilla hachi
yodim shelo para lo hashtar dehainu sheyecholinn lomar sheyintan lo karka umazik
ein lo yachzir aleihem. Okay, meaning I don't get him, like, you
know, he's got to pay you first. How would we ever leapfrog
the seller? All right, we're going to go to him and make
sure that he can't pay you off. How would I ever do
it? וכסברת רשב״י אם יכול לסלקו בזוזי אם לאו ונהי דמסיק לסלוקי
Ukesvarat Rashbi im yachol lesalko bezuzi im lav v'nehi demasik lesiluki says
and because of this גמרא Gemara it was a little uncertain. Can
the seller, if all he has is cash, can he pay the
guy up with cash or does he have to give the guy
קרקע? karka? And it says, it would seem like you're always entitled
to give the guy cash. But none of this makes any sense,
because whatever the reality is, whether the seller has to give land
or has to give, these guys do not give up their land
unless they have good proof that the seller has been involved in
this process and hasn't been able to pay off. So this whole
גמרא Gemara is very strange. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos raised the question,
I don't know what the answer is. Okay, now we go on.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, moving on. He's into something fishy too. There
you go, שייכי shaichi Michael. We heard, which is not, which is
not the way to understand. All right, not what anybody says, but
you can go with that, Michael. אמר מר חוץ מן אחריות שבו
חוץ מן אחריות שבו. Amar Mar chutz min achrayus shebo, chutz min
achrayus shebo. Okay, היכי כתבינן? Heichi katvinan? Now, when we give me
this שטר shtar? without the אחריות, achrayus what does it say? I
bought this land but I don't have insurance. So what does it
say? So אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman דכתבי הכי, dechasvi hachi,
here's what's written. שטר דנן דלא ליגני ביה, Shtar denan delo lignei
bei, this שטר shtar that you own this piece of land, it
does not give you the right to collect if it's taken from
you, לא ממשעבדי, lo mimshabdei, not from anything with liens, ולא מנכסי,
vlo minichsei, not even from stuff that the original seller still has.
If this land is taken from you, you're out. Okay, אלא כי
היכי דתקום ארעא ביד דלוקח. Ela ki heichi detikum ara beyad delokayach.
The only reason you have this is to prove that it's yours,
but there's absolutely you are not entitled to any insurance on this
land. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, I'm sorry, so רבא Rava says, זאת
אומרת, Zos omeres, the fact that you had to explicitly say there's
no insurance means that if you said nothing insurance would be implicit.
Okay, זאת אומרת אחריות טעות סופר הוא. Zos omeres achrayus tao sofer
hu. So אחריות טעות סופר הוא achrayus tao sofer hu means the
fact if the absence of there being אחריות achrayus? insurance written in
a שטר, shtar the liens written in a שטר, whether it's a
loan that I leaned on property that the borrower has or whether
it's a bill of sale and that the person who's buying it
has liens on my property, if it gets taken from him, if
it's not written, it was just an oversight. Okay, but it is
always assumed. אחריות achrayus. is always assumed, and therefore if you want
to exclude אחריות, achrayus. you have to explicitly exclude it. טעמא דכתב
ליה הכי, Taama dechasav lei hachi, the only reason there's no אחריות
achrayus. is you explicitly excluded it. הא לא כתב ליה הכי זבי,
Ha lo chasav lei hachi zavi, you would be entitled. So the
absence is not enough. Okay, אחריות achrayus. is always there unless you
explicitly exclude it. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav
Ashi says אחריות לאו טעות סופר הוא. achrayus lav tao sofer hu.
Nope, אחריות achrayus is not a טעות סופר. tao sofer. If it's
not there, then it was meant to not be there. Okay, so
what does it mean we write me a שטר without אחריות? achrayus.
ומה חוץ מאחריות שבו? Uma chutz meachrayus shebo? דלא כתב ביה אחריות,
Delo chasav bei achrayus, very simply. It means we write me a
שטר and we don't explicitly include the אחריות. achrayus Okay, so that's
the question. This charge doesn't have אחריות. achrayus. Does it mean it's
explicitly excluded or does it mean just by not being written it
doesn't exist? So that's the question of whether by default we assume
there's אחריות. achrayus Now here's a story. ההיא אתתא דיהבה ליה זוזי
לההוא גברא Hahi itta deyahava lei zuzai lehahu gavra למיזבן לה ארעא.
lemizban lah ara. A woman gave money to a man to go
buy land for her. אזל זבנה לה דלא באחריות. Azal zavnah lah
delo bachrayus. He bought the land without אחריות. achrayus Okay, he bought
the land without insurance, which was really stupid. So אתיא לקמיה דרב
נחמן, Asya lekamei deRav Nachman, came to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Now,
by the way, רב נחמן Rav Nachman was the one that just
said above, which one was רב נחמן Rav Nachman said? That that
that you have to explicitly exclude. So which means that this guy
did something really stupid. He bought the land and not only did
he not get the אחריות achrayus written in the שטר, he agreed
to a שטר that explicitly excluded אחריות. achrayus. Okay, maybe the guy
said I'll only sell it to you if we exclude אחריות achrayus
and he agreed to it. Right, right, so אמר ליה, amar lei,
so אמר ליה. amar lei. You were sent basically to—it says אמרה
ליה, amra leh, I don't know why it says אמרה ליה amra
leh because it's the woman who sent her, but maybe it means
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to the man, you were sent to
operate on her best interest, not to do something that was going
to hurt her. Buy land without insurance, even if you got a
better deal, is never a better deal, okay? So you always need
to buy the insurance, that's the way it is with land, and
to do that unless she explicitly authorized you to, whatever, you know,
buy it without insurance, then it was not valid. Now, if that's
true, you should say the whole sale is invalid, okay? But let's
see what רב נחמן Rav Nachman says: זיל זבנה מיניה שלא באחריות
והדר זבנה ניהלה באחריות.
Zil zavna mineh shelo be'achrayus vehadar zavnah
nihala be'achrayus. Go buy it from the original seller, presumably if the
original sale never went through. So, okay, if the original sale never
went through, why don't we just say, fine, let her now try
to buy it from the original guy? But if he let's say
originally bought it from the original guy for ten thousand dollars without
אחריות. achrayus. So now somehow he has to—and with אחריות achrayus the
guy was charging eleven thousand dollars.
So now he says, okay, here's what you're going to do now.
Buy it now in your own name from that guy for ten
thousand dollars, which is right, without אחריות because he's willing to sell
it without
אחריות for ten thousand dollars,
and now turn around and sell it to the woman for the
same ten
thousand dollars with אחריות.
So now if something happens to it, you're going to have to
be the one—you're essentially providing the insurance on this piece of land.
Now, I don't exactly get why that's true. Why don't we just
say the שליחות shlichus was בטל, batel, he didn't operate in her
best interest, the מוכר mocher gives the money back, right, and now
negotiate everything anew? It's like it seems like this real fine that
we're imposing on this guy. You, since you bought it for ten
thousand dollars, she's going to now get it for ten thousand dollars,
but you're the one who's going to provide the insurance. It would
seem like the original seller—buyer or seller—would have to give the money
back. The original sale wasn't good, right? And now you rebuy it
from the guy at the same price without אחריות and sell it
to the woman at that price with אחריות. So basically you're now
going to provide the אחריות for free. I don't understand why the
original sale isn't good, I mean it's not the seller's fault, whatever.
No, so that's—because we—this is always an interesting case that we've seen
in the גמרא. Gemara. If I make somebody a שליח shaliach to
represent me in a transaction and they do something that was not
in my interest, I can always say the שליחות shlichus was בטל,
batel, which, as when we learned this in previous גמרות Gemoras I
always said, any smart businessman therefore will always have somebody operating for
them in a transaction, right, because then they could always make the
claim, "Oh, this wasn't in my best interest, the sale was בטל"
batel or whatever. And he represents himself as a שליח shaliach and
the seller would have a way of knowing? Right, but he's just
buying it, right? No, I mean, well no, the שטר would be
written for the person you're representing. So yeah, you do know that
this person's a שליח. shaliach. It is a strange הלכה halacha that
basically—that you authorize somebody and, you know, and you would think that
if they're authorized, then that gives them the discretion to make those
decisions. But the fact is that you can at certain—at certain times
the משלח meshaleach can say, "No, that wasn't in my best interest,
so the whole שליחות shlichus is בטל." batel. This has come up
multiple times in the גמרא, Gemara, and we've pointed out the problem
with it is that it makes it—like anybody who's smart will never
do any business transaction—you would never do any business transaction with you
and with the other person's שליח. shaliach. If the other person's a
שליח, shaliach, you're going to send a שליח. shaliach. But then, you
know, how does anything ever get done because each side's going to
find an excuse to back—I don't know the answer. Anyway, but also
what's strange here is that the בית דין Beis Din instead of
just saying the sale was בטל, batel, the person is actually being
fined essentially to provide the insurance. Okay, let's read a little bit
more. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הנותן מתנה לחברו והחזיר לו את
השטר חזרה מתנתו. Ve-Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer hanosein matana le-chavero ve-hechezir
lo es ha-shtar chazra matanaso. So anyway, this explains why he says
we don't even write a שטר שלא באחריות, shelo be'achrayus, because we
discussed this earlier, because if you give back the original שטר, that
reverses the sale. And therefore we're afraid that that's what happens. וחכמים
אומרים מתנתו קיימת, Ve-Chachamim omrim matanaso kayames, even if you give back
the original שטר that does not reverse the sale. The גמרא Gemara
says, מאי טעמא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Mai ta'ama de-Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel? What's the reason? אמר רב אסי נעשה כאומר לו שדה זו
נתונה לך כל זמן שהשטר בידך. Amar Rav Assi na'aseh ke-omer lo
sade zu netuna lecha kol zman she-ha-shtar beyadecha. It's like when I
sell you the field, there's a תנאי. tnai. You own this field
as long as you still are holding on to the שטר. So
that can't be. מתקיף לה רבא. Masif lah Rava. Rava said: אי
הכי נגנב או אבד נמי? I hachi nignav o avad nami? So
even if the שטר was stolen or lost or burned or whatever,
would we say it got reversed? It's not some תנאי tnai that
as soon as you don't have the שטר, you know, the sale
is no longer good. אלא אמר רבא באותיות נקנות במסירה קמיפלגי. Ella
amar Rava be-osiyos niknos be-mesira kamiflagi. The question is, can you transfer
a שטר by the handing over of a שטר? Now, normally the
way that works is, I've got a שטר here, and this שטר
says that אליהו Eliyahu owes me a thousand dollars. And Michael, I'm
having a real hard time getting that money from אליהו, Eliyahu, so
I'm willing to sell this for nine hundred dollars. And Michael's willing
to buy it for nine hundred dollars, he thinks he can get
the money out of אליהו. Eliyahu. So he gives me nine hundred
dollars and I sell him the debt. So how do you transfer...
The letters in the שטר *shtar* נקנות במסירה *niknos bemesira*, meaning not
the physical document but what they represent are transferred by the just
holding of it. Now the other opinions are no, no, no, as
Michael wants to buy the debt, I give him the original שטר
*shtar* and I write another שטר *shtar* in his name that says
that now Eli owes you the money and so on. Okay, which
makes a lot of sense, right? Otherwise, maybe I dropped the שטר
*shtar* and he picked it up and now he's claiming it's his
or whatever. Although that could happen too; I could drop a diamond
ring and he could pick it up. Okay, but this is the
question: does the transfer of the שטר *shtar* transfer, even though it's
written in my name, transfer the debt? So what the גמרא *Gemara*
is saying is if you say that about a debt you would
say it about a קרקע *karka* on property. This שטר *shtar* says
that I bought Eli's field. If I hand it over to Michael,
even though it says Dov bought Eli's field, if he's holding on
to it, that means that he now owns the field. It's now
proof; it becomes it's not just proof, but we're talking about a
קנין *kinyan*. It's the act that transfers the property. So normally we
say that a קרקע *karka* is acquired with a שטר *shtar*. The
שטר *shtar* here now is not a שטר *shtar* written in Michael's
name. The שטר *shtar* is written in my name of the year,
but the act of me giving this שטר *shtar*—I might have bought
it from Eli, and the irony is that I could have bought
it from Eli like twenty years ago, fifty years ago, and I'm
selling it to Michael now. This old שטר *shtar* is a bill
of sale. It kind of makes sense if you think like about
a deed; like you buy your car, you get the deed or
whatever it is, the house, whatever. But the handing over of this
old bill of sale that's in my name, right, to Michael, basically
means that that's like Michael's קנין שטר *kinyan shtar* on that property.
So therefore if Michael, if Eli sold me the field and then
I give him back the שטר *shtar*, I'm basically giving him back
the field the same way if I gave the שטר *shtar* to
Michael, Michael owns the field. If I give the שטר *shtar* back
to Eli, Eli now owns it.
As a loan doesn't require a שטר *shtar* at all, effectively. Right.
Unlike קרקע *karka*. קרקע *karka* could also be acquired without a שטר
*shtar*.
That's a different theory.
So some people want to say that
the שטר *shtar* is just a proof of the existence of the
loan, and you're trying to turn this into—but that's better!
If even a שטר *shtar* which is just a proof of the
existence of a loan could be a way of transferring the loan,
then the שטר *shtar* which itself was the vehicle to take possession
of the land should be more of a basis for saying that
by handing over the שטר *shtar* it's the act again.
Right. But I mean like I can understand.
I know, but the standard
case of a
שטר *shtar* for proof.
Right. Not for the קנין *kinyan* itself.
Right. Well, okay, but fine. Anyway, the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to—we get.
The standard case is by a loan; there could be an argument
to say that by actually by a שטר *shtar* for קרקע *karka*,
maybe it's easier to work by handing it over because the whole
nature of a שטר קרקע *shtar karka* is an instrument of the
קונה *koneh*. That's true, although that's the rarer case that we discussed
it. But the other question that David asked just now and Dov
asked me is that you know, what if somebody just finds the
שטר *shtar*? Is the שטר *shtar* the act of קנין *kinyan*? But
then you need to prove that it actually was given in that
way, or is the very holding of it proof enough? So you
could say the very holding of it is proof enough. Michael could
sneak into my house, steal my שטר *shtar*, and then claim he
owns my house. You know what? True. But he could also sneak
into my house and steal all my my diamonds and claim he
owns my diamonds. Okay. אין הכי נמי *Ein hachi nami*. But okay,
but anyway, but you're right. That is a separate question that you
might need עדים *eidin* to prove that it was given over in
that way. That's going to get discussed in the גמרא *Gemara*. But
the first thing we're dealing with is not proof, but whether the
very act effects the transfer. Okay, so we'll just read that one
line again and then with that we'll end. ואותיות נקנות במסירה כמאן
דאמר אותיות נקנות במסירה *Ve'osiyos niknos bemesira kman de'amar osiyos niknos bemesira*
and therefore the handing over of the שטר *shtar* to the original
owner transfers the property back to him. If you gave it to
somebody else, it would transfer the property to the other person. ורבנן
סברי אין אותיות נקנות במסירה *Verabanan savri ein osiyos niknos bemesira*. It
does not transfer the property. Okay, and we will continue with this
tomorrow.
Oh,
is this still recording? Yeah. This
is looking much less good in my eyes. What
was that? I give it back to him?
Yeah. What's up?
That was the best. What's up?
Do you know what we just did? Yeah. 169.
You
know this is just pretty,
pretty amazing. There's nothing new under the sun. There were prostitutes then;
there are prostitutes today.